Finding Aid for the M. A. Zeitlin Collection of Reproduced Manuscripts in Spanish LSC.1264
UCLA Library Special Collections
M.A. Zeitlin Collection of Reproduced Manuscripts in Spanish
circa 1931-1993
UCLA Library Special Collections
Zeitlin, M.A. (Marion Albert)
LSC.1264
1.0 Linear Feet (2 boxes)
M. A. Zeitlin (1899-1993) was a professor in UCLA's Department of Spanish and Italian, founded the departmental program in Portuguese, helped to develop a curriculum in Latin American studies, and was a member of the initial committee on Latin American Studies. The collection consists of photographic copies and one transcription of manuscripts in Spanish.
Restrictions on Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Gift of Marion A. Zeitlin, October, 1980.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9942340573606533
Biography
Zeitlin was born on August 29, 1899 in Chicago. He moved to Arizona and attended the University of Arizona where he received his B.A. in 1918. In 1920 he earned his M.A. from Stanford University. Zeitlin continued his study of French in Brussels and at the Sorbonne. He accepted a teaching position at the University of California Southern Branch in 1925. Two years later, he moved to Berkeley, and earned a Ph.D in romance languages with Spanish as a major from UC Berkeley in 1931. Zeitlin returned to UCLA that same year as an assistant professor, later becoming chair of the Department of Spanish and Italian, as well as a full professor. During his professorship, he founded the departmental program in Portuguese, helped to develop a curriculum in Latin American studies, and was a member of the initial committee on Latin American Studies. In 1967 he was named Comendador of the Ordem do Infante Dom Henrique by the Portuguese government and in 1968 he was awarded the title of Oficial of the Ordem Nacional do Cruzeiro do Sul. Additionally, he was awarded the UCLA Medal for Distinguished Service in 1980. After the death of his wife Zell in 1967, he married Frances Kirschenbaum, the medieval and renaissance bibliographer at the UCLA University Research Library. Zeitlin died on September 8, 1993.
Scope and Content
The collection consists of photographic copies and holograph transcriptions of manuscripts in Spanish. Works in this collection of facsimiles include various books of the Bible, originally housed in the Escorial library of Spain, as well as other medieval works from Isidore of Seville and Pedro López de Ayala.
Related Material
M.A. Zeitlin Papers (Collection 353). Available at UCLA Library Special Collections.
Language teachers -- California -- Los Angeles -- Archives.; University of California, Los Angeles. Department of Spanish and Portuguese--Faculty -- Archives; Zeitlin, M.A. (Marion Albert)
- Bible, s. xiv1, in Spanish, Escorial I.j.6, from Proverbs through Apocalypse, fol. 1-196v, on photographic prints (5x7"). (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Bible, s. xiv1, in Spanish, Escorial I.j.6, from Proverbs through Apocalypse, fol. 197-358, on photographic prints (5x7"). (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Bible, s. xiv1, in Spanish, various books, fol. 1 - 93v, on photographic prints (5x7"). (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Bible, s. xiv1, in Spanish, various books, fol. 94- 357v, on photographic prints (5x7"). (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Holograph transcription, St. Isidore of Seville (ca. 560-636 C.E.), De Summo Bono, n.d., on paper (5.5x8.5"), approx. 220 pp., unbound. (Box 1, Folder 4)
- López de Ayala, Pedro (1332-1407), Rimado del Palacio, s. xv, on photographic prints (7x9.5"), fol. 1-141. (Box 2, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  Note: Facsimile of Ms. 4055 from the Biblioteca Nacional de España.
- 1López de Ayala, Pedro (1332-1407), Razon del la Union de la Iglesia, n.d., fol. 68v-72r, holograph transcription on paper (9x5.5") and on photographic prints (7x9.5"). (Box 2)
  Note: Facsimile of Esp. 216 from the Bibliothèque Nationale de France.
- 22López de Ayala, Pedro (1332-1407), Rimado del Palacio, n.d., Escorial III.h.19, fol. 1-79v, on photographic prints (7x9.5").
- 23López de Ayala, Pedro (1332-1407), Rimado del Palacio, n.d., Escorial III.h.19, fol. 80-161v, on photographic prints (7x9.5").
- 24López de Ayala, Pedro (1332-1407), Flores de los Morales de Job, s. xiv/xv, Escorial II.b.7, fol. 1-106v, on photographic prints (7x9.5").
  Note: Includes Ayala's excerpts from St. Gregory's Moralia in Job.
- 2St. Isidore of Seville (ca. 560-636 C.E.), De Soberano Bien, n.d., on paper (9x6.5"), 112 pp., bound in green cloth hardcover with gilt spine title lettering.